Guide to the Jack Preiss papers, 1940-2012
Duke University. University Archives
Jack Preiss papers 1940-2012
Duke University. University Archives
Preiss, Jack Joseph, 1919-.
1.75 linear feet Extent: 300 Items
Jack Joseph Preiss taught in the Dept. of Sociology at Duke University from 1959-1988. The materials in the collection pertain to Preiss' time at Camp William James in Vermont and race relations at Duke. The collection includes correspondence, photographs, clippings, and posters. It ranges in date from 1940-2012.
uapreiss
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Jack Preiss papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1967 and 2013.
Biographical Note
Jack Joseph Preiss was born in New York City in 1919. He received his A.B. from Dartmouth College in 1940, his M.A. from Columbia University in 1951, and his Ph.D. from Michigan State University in 1954. He joined the faculty at Duke University in 1959 and served in both the Dept. of Sociology and the Dept. of Psychiatry. He retired in 1988 and is a Professor Emeritus in Sociology. Active within the community, Preiss served on the Durham City Council from 1965-1969 and has worked since 1985 to help develop and obtain low-income housing for seniors.
Collection Overview
This collection consists of letters from Preiss to his mother, Mrs. Mary Sacks Preiss, and her two sisters, but there are some letters to Preiss from several friends whom he had met in a work-service camp in Tunbridge, Vermont [Camp William James]. The correspondence by Preiss is largely about the problems of organizing and operating the work-service camp, its being taken over by the CCC, the resignation of himself and some others from the CCC, and the re-establishment of the work-service camp. He also, however, writes quite a bit about social affairs.
The work-service idea was put into practice by Dr. Eugen Rosenstock-Huessy, who taught social philosophy at Dartmouth and had founded the pre-Hitler work camps in Germany. He got some young, city boys of privileged backgrounds to join him in establishing the camp at Tunbridge. The camp was named for Professor William James, who had lectured on a moral equivalent of war, and the purpose of the camp was to give these men from the city experience in aiding farmers with their labor, in the hope that each group would profit from their association with each other and the farmers would have some much-needed labor. Dorothy Thompson, who had a summer home in the valley of the camp, gave this project continual assistance and encouragement. Preiss comments on her and her support in his letters.
The collection also includes clippings, largely about the work-service camp and several black and white photographs, presumably of the work-camp. In 2013, Dr. Preiss donated material on race relations at Duke. Included in this accession are two posters from Black Week at Duke, information on the 1988 Duke Vigil Reunion, Alan Kerckhoff's committee and his chronology of campus race relation events from 1969, a 1968 issue of Sports Illustrated with an article on Preiss and Duke called The Timid Generation, an unpublished Preiss manuscript about race relations at Duke and other material.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Camp William James -- History; Clippings; Race relations -- North Carolina -- Durham; Student movements -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.)--Race relations
Bibliography
Preiss, Jack Joseph Camp William James,
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Photographs, undated (Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1940-1942 (Folder 2)
  - Miscellany, 1940-1941 (Folder 3)
  - The Harvard Progressive and Free America, 1941-1942 (Folder 4)
  - Letter, 1969 (Folder 5)
  - Clippings (Folder 6)
  - Sports Illustrated, 1968 March 11 (article The Timid Generation) (Folder 7)
  - Alan Kerckhoff Committee, 1968-1969 (Folder 8)
  - African and Afro-American Studies Planning Conference, 1969 (Folder 9)
  - Manuscript on Race Relations at Duke, circa 1973 (pgs. 1-21) (Folder 10)
  - Manuscript on Race Relations at Duke, circa 1973 (pgs. 22-48) (Folder 11)
  - Manuscript on Race Relations at Duke, circa 1973 (pgs. 49-86) (Folder 12)
  - Manuscript on Race Relations at Duke, circa 1973 (footnotes) (Folder 13)
  - Vigil Reunion, 1988 (Folder 14)
  - Program: NAACP Freedom Fund Banquet (honoring Jack Preiss), 2012 Oct. 27 (Folder 15)
  - Black Week at Duke Posters, 1968-1969 (Opaperfolder 1)
  - harambee, 1969 Feb. 5 issue (Opaperfolder 1)
  - The Chronicle supplement The Silent Vigil: 20 Years Later, 1988 Apr. 4 (Opaperfolder 1)